只有一种生物为了自己的生存
Only one creature has carved a life for itself
在地球的每一个角落都留下了印迹
in every habitat on earth.
那就是人类
That creature is us.
天地悠悠
All over the world,
我们仍依靠创造力来努力存活于世
we still use our ingenuity to survive in the wild places,
远离文明开化的城市
far from the city lights,
直面原始险恶的自然
face to face with raw nature.
沙漠是地球上最热最干的地方
Deserts are the hottest and driest places on earth.
它们覆盖着地表的三分之一
They cover one third of the land surface.
有些地区一雨难求
Some never see rain.
我们可以两个月不吃东西
We can survive two months without food,
但不喝水则活不了几天
yet only a few days without water.
作为胎儿  我们被液体包围着
As babies, we spend nine months
要在母亲的子宫里待上九个月
surrounded by fluid in our mother's womb.
但分娩之后  我们再无幸享受那奢华的水世界
But birth pushes us out of this luxurious water world.
从这一刻起
From this point on,
能否找到充足的水
life for every child of the desert
决定了沙漠里每一个孩子的生命
is defined by the quest for water.
难以置信的是
Yet somehow, in this brutal land,
在这片残酷的土地上有三亿人生存了下来
an incredible 300 million people survive.
以下就是他们的非凡故事
These are their remarkable stories.
沙漠
熔炉中的生命
撒哈拉是全球最大的沙漠
The Sahara is the biggest desert on the globe.
其面积堪比美国
It is the size of the United States,
从它干旱的内陆
and its arid interior can
可释放出地球上最强势的沙尘暴
unleash the mightiest sandstorms on the planet.
猛烈的狂风卷起成万上亿颗细小的沙粒
Ferocious winds whip up billions of tiny sand grains
形成一堵巨大的沙墙
into massive walls.
五千米高的沙墙拔地而起
Reaching more than 5,000 metres into the air,
其高度是帝国大厦的十倍
ten times the height of the Empire State Building,
其面积足以覆盖大不列颠
covering areas the size of Britain.
一名16岁的男童玛玛杜
Battling through this sandstorm in Mali
在马里的沙尘暴中挣扎求生
is 16-year-old Mamadou.
他是一个牧牛人  三天前离开家
He's a cattle herder who left home three days ago
踏上为牛寻水的征途
on a mission to find water for his cows.
奶牛就是我的命
它们维持着全家的生活
如果找不到水  奶牛就会死
他稚幼的双肩扛起了无比艰巨的责任
It's a huge responsibility on his teenage shoulders.
他必须独自忍受沙漠的盛怒
He must endure the fury of the desert alone,
但前方  更大的挑战在等着他
but there's an even bigger challenge ahead.
他在与地球上最大的陆地动物赛跑
He's in a race against the biggest land animal on earth--
非洲象
African elephants.
它们同样渴望得到水的滋润
This desert herd is also desperate for water
因为全马里都深陷干旱的魔爪
because Mali is gripped by drought.
这里有40摄氏度
It's 40 degrees Celsius.
大部分水坑均已干涸
Most of the water holes are already dry.
只有80公里外的一个地方仍会有水
Only one place for 80 kilometres will still have water--
斑泽纳湖
Lake Banzena.
这里就是非洲象和玛玛杜的目的地
And this is where both the elephants and Mamadou are heading.
我必须在大象之前...
...赶到湖边
如果它们先到达  我的牛就只能吃泥了
如果玛玛杜保持快速行进
If Mamadou keeps up a fast pace,
他就会在天亮时分到达湖边
he'll reach the lake by morning.
但就在他身后50公里的地方
But only 50 kilometres behind him
沙漠族群中最大的游牧族也在蠢蠢欲动
are the greatest nomads of the desert.
母象族长带领着象群
Elephant matriarchs guide the herd,
循着方圆几百几千公里内
following an incredible mental map of all the water holes
由诸多水坑标记的奇妙记忆地图
to be found in an area
向湖边进发
of tens of thousands of square kilometres.
刺槐树为它们的旅途提供了充足的供给
Acacia trees give them just enough fuel to keep walking,
但它们不能停息  必须日夜行进
but they can't rest, day or night.
但是对于玛玛杜来说
But, for Mamadou,
黑夜令他别无选择  只能停歇
nightfall means he has no choice but to stop.
在黑暗中遇上象群是致命的
Meeting elephants in the dark could be fatal.
玛玛杜从奶牛那挤出几丝珍贵的牛奶
A hurried breakfast is the little precious milk
凑成了一顿匆忙的早餐
Mamadou can get from his cows.
这可以暂时防止他脱水
It keeps him one step away from dehydration.
但他必须得前进了
But he's got to get going.
象群走了一夜
The elephant herd have walked through the night,
渐渐逼近
making up ground.
终于  湖水映入了玛玛杜的眼帘
Finally the end is in sight for Mamadou.
但麻烦正等着他
But he walks straight into trouble.
庞大的象群不仅先他一步到达湖边
Not only have the massive elephant herd beaten him to the lake,
还堵住了他前进寻水的道路
but they're also blocking his access to the water.
玛玛杜深知万象奔腾的威力
Mamadou knows the elephants could charge,
所以他很小心  不过于接近象群
so he is careful not to get too close.
冲突一触即发
It's an uneasy truce
同时他还要想出突破重围的办法
while he works out how to break through.
突然间  一头大象向他的牛群冲去
Suddenly an elephant charges his cows.
玛玛杜给予了反击  但他只有树枝可用
Mamadou fights back, but armed only with sticks,
这简直就是大卫和歌利亚之间的战斗
it's a battle of David and Goliath.
出自《旧约》:  歌利亚是巨人  大卫为了奖赏与之搏杀
玛玛杜鼓起勇气赶走了五十多头大象
Mamadou's courage has managed to shift over 50 elephants.
幸运的是  这样的情况极少
Luckily, conflicts like this are very rare.
大象被口渴逼疯了...
就像我们一样
终于  玛玛杜赶着他的牛群
Finally Mamadou drives his cattle
走向这生命之水
towards the life-giving water.
象群离开  去寻找这片湖中自己的领域
The elephants move off and find their own part of the lake.
最终  它们也饮上了水
At last, they too have an opportunity to drink...
甚至玩耍起来
and even play.
两个月内将没有雨水填满那些水坑
It will be two months before there's any chance of rain replenishing the water holes,
所以玛玛杜还得继续奋斗
so Mamadou's struggles will go on.
但在沙漠的一隅
But in one part of the desert,
水源的吃紧却带来了意外之喜
a shrinking water supply leads to a surprising opportunity.
几百公里开外  沿着邦贾加拉峭壁
Hundreds of kilometres away, along the Bandiagara escarpment,
40度的热浪袭来
the sapping 40-degree heat has sucked the life
夺走了多贡河的生机
out of the rivers of Dogon country,
只留下孤零零的水坑
leaving only isolated pools
满是搁浅的鱼
stuffed with stranded fish.
多贡人将此时定为沙漠捕鱼节
The Dogon choose this moment for a desert fishing festival.
上千名竞争者被吸引到安图果湖
Thousands of competitors are drawn to Lake Antogo,
其中包括迪亚罗  他30年来  一直来这
including Dialo, who's been coming here for 30 years.
能抓到鱼对他来说是一种荣耀
It's a matter of pride for him to catch a fish.
来这里的人都想抓到鱼
...所以竞争很激烈
虽然没法保证  但我会尽力抓一两条鱼
如果成功了  我会十分欣慰
在其它任何日子里
On any other day,
捕鱼在这片神圣水域是严令禁止的
fishing is strictly forbidden in this sacred water.
久而久之  那些长者就为旱季贮存下了
In this way, the elders protect an important food reserve
重要的食物储备
well into the dry season.
但今日  这个群落有机会
But today the community
收获一顿"最后的晚餐"
have a chance to catch a symbolic last supper.
河岸很快就挤满了人
The banks are filling up quickly.
气氛很紧张
The atmosphere is tense.
迪亚罗已经找到一处好位置
Dialo has found a good spot.
但现在他必须等待
But now he must wait
因为安图果有自己不成文的规定
since Antogo has its own unwritten rules.
仪式酋长摇首颂祷  以驱散妖魔鬼怪
The ceremonial chief chants a prayer to chase away evil spirits.
他头罩鱼篓
He wears a fish trap,
相信这样能保护脱口而出的祷词
believed to protect the words as they are spoken.
这是迪亚罗一年一遇的机会
This is Dialo's once-a-year chance.
自由的捕鱼人迅速乱做了一团
The free-for-all quickly becomes a fishing frenzy.
他们将鱼篓猛塞进湖底抓鱼
They thrust their baskets down to trap the fish.
迪亚罗已经逮到了一条
Dialo has caught one,
但现在顾不得什么绅士礼节
but there's no time for politeness.
嘿  这是我的地盘
仅仅过了15分钟  湖里就一干二净了
After just 15 minutes, there's nothing left,
混乱渐渐平息
and the chaos subsides.
迪亚罗成功了  但也已精疲力尽
Dialo is successful, but exhausted.
回到家  他那傲人的收获
Back at home, his proud catch of fish
成了全家人最后的饕餮
becomes a final feast for his family
这样他们就能熬过旱季的尾巴
so they can survive the last days of the dry season.
当你抓到鱼  你就会感到那幸福之门
...为你和你的家人打开
用尽各种寻路绝技  才找的到水源
it takes immense navigational skill just to find water.
这些图布女人
These Tubu women must
必须冒险穿过浩瀚的撒哈拉沙海
venture across the vast sand seas of the Sahara
去寻找只有一平米见方的小井
in search of a miniature well just one metre square.
它意味着生与死的差别
It will mean the difference between life and death.
他们管这里叫泰内雷  不毛之地
They call this place the Tenere-- the land of nothing.
这里四无一物  炙热撩人  危机遍布
It is featureless, scorching and unreliable.
来自图布的菲尼
Foni is a Tubu woman who can
可以在没有地图或指针的情况下找到水源
find her way to water without a map or a compass.
我从小就来往与这条路线
这是全世界最艰难的一条路
她还带着她年仅十岁的女儿  莎黛
She's brought her daughter, Shede, only ten years old.
他们还要走上三天才能到达所寻之井
The well they seek is still three days' walk away.
这将是他们一起面对的最艰苦卓绝的旅程
This is the toughest journey they'll ever face together.
两个人死了  他们没找到井
我们向上帝祈求保护
他们肩负着这趟涉险寻食之旅
They undertake this perilous journey for food.
他们必须穿越240公里到达集市
They must cross 240 kilometres just to get to market
卖掉骆驼以换取六个月的供给
to trade camels for supplies that will last them six months.
这支队伍只有女人和小孩
This caravan is only women and children,
因为在图布  女人是认路能手
since, for the Tubu, it's the women who are the great navigators.
在没经验的肉眼看来
To the untrained eye,
沙丘就是一座沙丘
a dune is just a dune.
但菲尼可辨别出
But Foni can tell which ones
这变幻之地中的安全岛
to trust in a place where nothing stands still.
小一点的沙丘变幻着形状  随风而动
Smaller dunes shape-shift, moving with the wind,
隐藏着许多危机
making them unreliable.
但大一点的沙丘  堆积了60多米
But larger dunes, towering over 60 metres,
更加稳固  可供旅人对沙漠管中窥豹一番
are more stable, revealing signs of a much bigger picture.
几千年来  沙漠中的狂风
Over thousands of years, prevailing desert winds
将沙丘吹成平行的长沙脊
have blown dunes into long, parallel ridges,
它是旅人们可辨认的唯一地标
the only landmarks for the travellers.
图布人以观察太阳和脊线
The Tubu look to the sun and
来辨别该朝哪个方向走
the ridge line to work out which direction to go.
然后清点脊线的数目来看走了多远
Then they count each ridge to know how far they've gone.
他们已在焦阳下走了十个小时
They've been walking for ten hours in the blazing sun.
得歇一歇了
They must rest.
他们用一张床单扎营
They make their camp out of a single sheet,
并分配饮水
and ration their water.
骆驼的水里参夹了燕麦
The camels' share is mixed with oats,
女人则喝甜茶
while the women drink sweet tea.
菲尼  我们今天走了多少路
33个沙丘
没错  我掰手指数过
他们要赶在日头最盛前早起
They rise early, before the sun gets too hot.
他们只带了到达水井所必须的水
They only carry enough water to get to the well,
所以速度至关重要
so the pace they travel is key.
熟悉这方面沙漠知识的专家早已消失
This specialist understanding of the desert is fast disappearing.
现如今只有几百个图布妇女了解这些知识
Today only a few hundred Tubu women possess the knowledge.
菲尼相信把这些知识传授给莎黛
Foni believes that by teaching Shede
那知识就能代代流传  惠及后代
she can keep it alive for another generation.
莎黛听好  在到达水井前要经过八个山脊
当到达第九个时  你会看见一个灌木丛
水井就在第十个山脊后面
而当黑夜逐渐来临
When darkness falls,
菲尼就会教莎黛解读夜晚的天空
Foni also teaches Shede how to read the night sky.
那就是北极星
如果北极星一直在我们身后
...我们总会找到水井的
至少目前她们清楚方向是对的
For now, at least, they know they're on the right path.
今天是第三天
It's day three.
她们必须在今天之内找到水井
Today they must find the well.
收拾铺盖时  菲尼决定让莎黛来负责寻找水井
While packing up, Foni decides Shede is ready to take charge.
但水井十分隐蔽  即使只相距几百米
But the well is so hidden that even if she's
她也可能一不小心错过了
only a few hundred metres away, she could miss it.
她们朝着正确的方向出发
She sets them off in the right direction, aligning herself
走在山脊中间  朝着日出向东前进
between the ridges ahead and the sunrise to the east.
对像莎黛这样十来岁年纪的孩子来说
For some children Shede's age, just ten years old,
认准去学校的路已经不易
finding their way to school is challenge enough.
但是莎黛必须在这全世界最荒芜的地方
But Shede has to find her way
走上20公里找到目的地
20 miles across the bleakest landscape on Earth.
我一个人肯定吓死了
但有了妈妈的经验指导
But with her mother's guiding words echoing in her head,
她勇敢向前
she strides forward.
在繁重又辛苦的12小时之行后
After a gruelling 12-hours' riding,
第十个山脊终于近在眼前
the tenth ridge is finally in sight.
沙丘凹陷处的那一丛灌木
The lonely bush in the dip of the dune
是有水井那个溪谷的标志
marks the valley of the well.
就在那儿
就在那儿了
井在那
莎黛找到了80公里范围内唯一一个水井
Shede has found the only well for 80 kilometres around.
她的母亲为她自豪
She's made her mum proud.
终于  莎黛可以给骆驼喂水了
Finally, Shede can water the camels.
解决口渴问题之后  她洗了个澡
With their thirst quenched, she washes off three days of dust.
她们已经找到了水  接下来要运去市场
Now they've got water, they'll make it to market,
但离这次旅途的结束还有好几星期
but they're still weeks away from finishing their journey.
并非所有沙漠都酷热难当
Not all deserts are swelteringly hot.
蒙古的戈壁就代表了两个极端
The Gobi in Mongolia is a desert of extremes.
在距赤道遥远的北方
Lying far north of the equator,
炎夏的炼狱转瞬间就能变成北极的冰窖
here scorching summer highs plunge to freezing Arctic lows.
现在是二月份  零下20摄氏度
It's February, minus 20 degrees Celsius,
人们仅有的几个水井已经被冻住了
and the few wells people have are frozen over.
但是  雪是另一种形态的水
But, amazingly, water appears here as snow.
这里并不下雪
The snow doesn't fall here.
雪是从离这3000多公里的西伯利亚吹过来的
It's blown over 3,000 kilometres from Siberia.
而这些刺骨寒风从不消停
And these bitter winds mean it never settles for long.
所以冈包勒德和他的双驼峰
So Ganbold and his twin-humped Bactrian camels
必须循着雪花  向着它们所属的山脉赶去
must chase the snow towards the mountains where it lingers.
这珍贵的雪就是一条生命线
This rare snow is a lifeline.
雪即家人
滋养着兽群
事关重要  他和家人
It's so important, he and his family
已在山麓丘陵驻扎好营寨
have set up their winter camp in the foothills.
但这是一步险招
But he's taking a risk.
他的牧群  包括已经怀孕的雌兽
His herd, including pregnant females,
正处在沙漠肉食动物的窥视范围之内
are now in the hunting grounds of a voracious desert predator,
而它们的最爱  便是刚出生的骆驼幼仔
and they like nothing better than newborn camel flesh.
不能让骆驼长时间饮雪
狼群虎视眈眈
戈壁沙漠的狼群在几千公里范围内徘徊觅食
Gobi desert wolves roam over thousands of kilometres.
敏锐的触觉
Their keen sense of smell
能帮助他们追踪千里之外的猎物
helps them shadow the herds at a distance.
一旦冈包勒德稍有放松  它们就会发动袭击
If Ganbold drops his guard, they'll attack.
回到营地后
He returns to camp to hear
他得知自己的儿子已经阻止了一次狼群的袭击
that his son has interrupted a wolf attack.
它们杀死了一只羊
One sheep has been killed.
狼是贪婪的动物
来了一次  就会来第二次
暮色四合  沙尘暴开始肆虐
As evening falls, an icy dust storm builds.
狼群是温暖的帐篷中唯一的话题
In the warm tent, wolves are the only topic of conversation.
一旦狼抓住骆驼幼仔...
就咬断脖子  一击毙命
还喜欢在恶劣的天气干这些卑鄙勾当
午夜时分  冈包勒德最后一次检查了怀孕的骆驼
At midnight, Ganbold checks his pregnant camels one last time.
怎么只剩八只了
他突然意识到有雌骆驼失踪了
He suddenly realises his prize female is missing
但此刻风暴肆虐  只有等天亮才能去找
but, with the storm, they can't look for her until daylight.
天已经破晓  他们出发去寻找
Come dawn, the search is on to find out what has become of
那只母骆驼和它未出生的幼仔
her and her unborn calf.
走
别担心  我们会找到它的
冈包勒德召集了他的朋友
Ganbold musters his friends.
这是一场人类和狼群的较量
It's a race between them and the wolves.
他们发现了踪迹
They find tracks.
有只狼从这经过
冈包勒德走上最高的山脊
Ganbold heads to the highest ridge,
他对搜寻的规模也有了数
and the scale of his task becomes clear.
狼能辨别...
...孰强孰弱
发现了更多刚留下的足迹
More fresh tracks.
狼  是狼
我的枪有点晃
真是狡猾的动物
就差一点
真希望能抓住它
他们已经看到了敌人
They've seen off the enemy,
但是骆驼在附近吗
but is the camel nearby?
最后  他们隐约看到了骆驼的轮廓
Finally, they see a shape.
冈包勒德心爱的骆驼还活着
Ganbold's beloved camel is alive.
她已经产下了幼仔
And she's given birth.
骆驼幼仔还不能走动
But the calf isn't moving.
让他欣慰的是  幼仔还有呼吸
To his great relief, the calf is breathing.
所有人都会为小骆驼感到自豪
看样子还是站不起来
生出才几小时的骆驼是没法走回营地的
Only a few hours old, the calf is too weak to walk back to camp.
所以冈包勒德捎了它一程
So Ganbold gives it a lift.
他的儿子立刻跑出来帮忙
His son rushes out to help
其他孩子也凑过来围观这位新成员
and his other boys meet the latest addition to the herd.
冈包勒德为自己的好运感恩
Ganbold gives thanks for his good fortune.
不像戈壁  有些沙漠是与水无缘的
Unlike the Gobi, there are some deserts where water never exists.
在智利的阿塔卡马沙漠
In the Chilean Atacama desert,
有些地方就似火星表面一样荒芜
some areas are as desolate as the surface of Mars.
这是地球上最干燥的地方
This is the driest place on Earth.
这里的人们受大自然启发
Here people have been inspired
从稀薄的空气里祈求水源
by nature to conjure water from thin air.
南美洲的一种野生骆驼  驼马
Cactus flowers are a source of food for the guanacos,
以仙人掌花为食
the wild camels of South America.
这些仙人掌也是它们的饮水之源
But these cacti are also the key to their water supply.
它们被毛茸茸的青苔所覆盖
They're covered in furry lichen,
青苔会吸收空气中的湿气
which traps any moisture in the air.
奥兰多从仙人掌处获得了启发
Orlando has taken inspiration from the cacti's natural solution.
他和朋友一起竖起了一张六米高的大网
With his friends, he erects a vast net six metres high.
用力拉  查理
网的网眼就好比青苔的毛须
The net's mesh is designed to mimic the lichen hairs,
在阿塔卡马的的沿海地带
because in this coastal strip of the Atacama desert
太平洋的水气便是他们的生命线
they have a lifeline to moisture- the Pacific Ocean.
冰冷的洋流冷却了沙漠的空气
Here, cold sea currents cool the hot desert air
并氤氲出大雾
and produce huge fog blankets.
雾漂上岸
The fog is sucked ashore...
掠过仙人掌
..and sweeps over the cacti...
和奥兰多的网
..and also Orlando's nets.
当雾接触到仙人掌  就会在青苔的毛须上凝聚
When the fog hits the cacti, it condenses onto the lichen hairs,
这就获得了珍贵的水
which capture the precious water.
很快  仙人掌上就有露水滴下来
In no time, the cacti are dripping with dew.
在网上  也会发生同样的进程
On the nets, the fog does exactly the same.
一滴接一滴
Drop by precious drop,
水就奇迹般地流入了蓄水池
this miracle water is channelled to a reservoir.
别人看到我们
每天上山取水...
...都认为我们疯了
查理  快看  有这么多水
这些神奇的网
Each day, these magical nets
每天能产生将近500公升的水
produce nearly 500 litres of water...
使得奥兰多能在沙子里种植些植物
..which allows Orlando to nurture a few plants in the sand.
但他另有宏图
But he has bigger ideas.
我梦想为部落从天上取水
黄沙漫漫  这仅仅是人类
This is just the latest innovation
在追寻水源的无尽道路上的又一次创新
in the eternal human quest to find water in the desert.
纵观世界  蚀痕雕刻了每一处地貌
Around the world, signs are etched in the landscape.
痕迹表明了哪曾有水流过
Scars show where water used to flow.
七千年前  撒哈拉沙漠中
7,000 years ago, the Sahara
遍布纵横交错的江河湖水
was crossed by a network of rivers and lakes,
而现在已悉数消失  演变成了沙漠
which disappeared as it turned to desert.
但现如今在这不毛之地  有些水源
Yet, in this now barren land, some of this water remains
依旧深深藏在地下的岩石中
deep in rocks underground.
在阿尔及利亚中部的巴阿马
In Ba'amar, central Algeria,
开发这些古老的水源是人们的独门绝技
their extraordinary skill is to tap into this ancient water.
但你必须知道怎么利用它
But you have to know how to harness it.
马佛笛今年70岁  一生都献给了沙漠里
Mafourdi is 70 years old, and committed to a life in the desert.
我们祈求上帝的帮助
早晨祷告完毕以后  他就出发寻找水源
Every morning after prayer, the men head off to find water.
带着坚定的信念
With stubborn devotion
以及简单的工具  他们凿出了一口井
and very simple tools, they have dug a well.
花了六个月的时间
It's taken them six months
他们才在沙漠中开凿出一口井
to carve out a shaft through the desert rock.
现在他们已经为这个最危险的任务做好了准备
Only now are they ready for their most dangerous mission.
作为年纪最大  经验最丰富的人
As the oldest and the most experienced,
马佛笛独自降入井中
Mafourdi climbs down alone.
一条九米深的垂直深井
It's a sheer nine-metre drop.
井底挖出了一条齐膝水道
At the bottom lies knee-deep water in hand-dug passages.
马佛笛深知维持水源的流动性的重要
Mafourdi knows they are vital to keep the water supply flowing.
但有太多人由于水道崩塌
But many men have been buried
而被活埋于此
alive down here when the walls have collapsed.
这些水均从岩石中渗出
The water seeps from the rocks themselves.
在石头中封存了千年的水
Mafourdi has released it
都被马佛笛释放了出来
from thousands of years trapped in the rock.
古时曾流淌在这上方的河流
This ancient water is all that's left of the
留下了这些远古的液滴
rivers that used to flow across the land above.
这口井对我们来说意味着生命
来自于水的生命是圣洁的
但是一口井还远远不够
But one well isn't enough.
最好的计策就是将几口井打通
The real trick is to connect several wells
造出一个地下水道
and create an underground channel of water.
马佛笛的邻居阿卜杜拉
Mafourdi's neighbour, Abdullah,
前半年也曾挖出一口井
has also been digging a well for the last six months.
就在今天  他们要打通两口井
Today's the day they're going to join up.
能听到我讲话吗
快打通了
快了  快了
能听到我讲话吗
能  当然能
但是阿卜杜拉必须把马佛笛独自留在此
But Abdullah must leave Mafourdi.
连通水道无疑是最危险的环节
Joining the tunnels is the most dangerous part.
拉上去
挖出了这么多泥石
With so much earth removed,
30英尺的岩石随时可能崩塌
30 foot of rock could collapse at any moment.
如果崩塌了  马佛笛必死无疑
It would crush Mafourdi, with no hope of escape.
回到地面后  阿卜杜拉诚心为马佛笛祷告
Back at the surface, Abdullah prays for Mafourdi.
愿真主护佑他
愿先知穆罕默德赐福
最终  马佛笛将两条水道打通了
Finally, Mafourdi has broken through.
但是井壁能支撑住吗
But will the walls hold?
欢迎回来  真主阿拉保佑你
现在它跟另一口井已经连通了
这条新隧道组成了一个更大的供水系统
This new channel is just part of a much bigger system.
700年来  一代一代的人
Every generation for the last 700 years
在这不停开凿新井  连通水道
has been digging new wells and connecting them up.
现在这里已经有800多口井
There are over 800 wells here now,
沙漠之下已有60公里长的水道
channelling water 60 kilometres under the desert floor.
水流在开凿的水道中
The passages are cut so that
缓缓沿着下坡流动
the water continually runs slightly downhill.
当它抵达了平地  就会分流至各个村庄
When it reaches the surface, it's divided up
在水的滋养下  村庄才得以安康
to sustain a village that otherwise wouldn't exist.
马佛笛利用他的那份水源
With his share of the water,
发展起一个绿洲来种植海枣
Mafourdi has created an oasis to grow date palms.
这一创举吸引了无数好奇的游客
And this attracts all sorts of surprising visitors.
一看见花园  我就喜从心来
它激励我努力为此劳作
一旦有了用之不竭的水源  没有什么是不可能的
Once you have a permanent water supply, anything's possible.
在美国内华达州
In America's state of Nevada,
拉斯维加斯将沙漠生存推向了一个极致
Las Vegas pushes desert living to the extreme.
它打破了一切常规
It breaks all the rules.
它是美国成长最迅速的城市之一
It is one of the fastest growing cities in the US,
个人用水量
using more water per person
几乎比全球任何地方都高
than almost anywhere else in the world.
人类真的实现了一个不可能的梦想吗
Is this humanity realising an impossible dream?
或者它只是一道霓虹  稍纵即逝
Or is it just a neon mirage?
人类文明蓬勃而起
The deserts of the world are
又因水源的枯竭而消亡
littered with ruins of boom-and-bust civilisations
最后便留下了一片沙海
where the water ran out.
佩特拉是约旦古代的一个城市
Petra in Jordan was an ancient city
曾经的水渠系统可以在一天内
which once had an aqueduct system
向2万人供应4亿公升的水
delivering 40 million litres of water a day to 20,000 people.
对大多数沙漠居民来说
For most desert dwellers,
贫乏的雨水便是生活所有的期盼
life revolves around the meagre rains.
雨水是熬过下一个炎年的希望
Only with rain can they hope to survive the next blazing year.
但在马里  绝不可轻信沙漠之雨
But in Mali, desert rains are anything but reliable.
也许一连几年  滴雨未下
Some years, they don't come at all.
但一旦下起来  村民也知道会是狂风暴雨
If they do, the villagers know they come violently,
所以粮仓得都做好防水准备
so they must make their granaries watertight.
大雨总是紧随沙尘暴接踵而来
The rains are preceded by sandstorms,
所以现在人们望着天
so now people watch the skies,
等待一场咆哮的沙暴
waiting for a rampaging wall of dust.
50公里宽
At 50 kilometres wide, and
前进时速达100公里的沙暴
advancing at a speed of 100 kilometres an hour,
迅速吞噬了整个村庄
the sandstorm engulfs the village in minutes.
但人们都知道这黑压压的一片是个好兆头
But people know this darkness is ultimately a good sign.
最终大雨倾泻而下
Finally the rain is unleashed.
短短20分钟达到的15厘米的降雨量
15 centimetres falls in 20 minutes,
让沙漠变成了溪流密布的网络
turning the desert into a network of streams.
一整年的等待  在这一刻化作了喜悦
Having waited all year, it's suddenly a moment to rejoice.
雨水改变着全世界每一片沙漠的景致
In deserts across the world, rains transform the landscape.
这一刻
This is the one moment when
生活不再为水源发愁
life is no longer about the quest for water.
压力消失了
The pressure's off.
对西非尼日尔的沃达贝人来说
For the Wodaabe people of Niger, West Africa,
这是他们求偶的最佳时机
this is their window of opportunity for love.
雨水丰沛的时候
When the rains are good enough,
他们能从孤立的生活中解脱出来
they can abandon their normally isolated lives.
在充足的食物及水的供应下  上百号沃达贝人
There's enough food and water to support a few hundred Wodaabe
聚集到一起  参加一场世上罕见的聚会
coming together for one of the most extraordinary gatherings
一场传宗接代的盛会
of fertility and flirtation in the world.
在这一派繁忙的景象之下
In this hive of activity is Djao.
迪吉奥步行了80公里
He's walked 80 kilometres
来参加一场格瑞沃尔的比赛
to be here for a contest called Gerewol.
这是一种两性之间的求偶舞蹈
It's a courtship dance for sex.
赢就意味着他将赢得一位情人
Winning means he'll get a new lover.
跳格瑞沃就是为了赢得一位情人...
哪怕这意味着抢别人的老婆
你可以娶她或云雨一番
今年很特别
This year is special.
这是六年大旱后第一次举办格瑞沃尔比赛
It's the first Gerewol after six years of drought,
所以大家都兴致高昂
so expectations are running high.
迪吉奥已经结婚了  他的妻子笛贝也在场
Djao is already married, and his wife Tembe is here, too.
事实上  这场庆典上到处都是已婚夫妻
Indeed, this festival is full of married couples.
沃达贝文化允许人们
Wodaabe culture allows both men and women
在这几天可以不顾结婚誓言
to set aside their marriage vows
并且不用为此感到耻辱
without stigma for these few days.
笛贝期待一场鱼水之欢
Tembe is up for a fling herself.
我已经发现了三个中意的男人了
但是她知道她的丈夫也是红人
But she knows her husband is also a great catch.
迪吉奥又帅又高...
...唱一嗓子好歌
身段性感
所以我才选择了他
但是这场调情比赛  女人才是评审
But, for this flirting contest, it's the women who choose
更令人称奇的是  男人们都化上了妆
and, surprisingly, the men who dress up.
迪吉奥的美貌  舞蹈和歌唱实力将被仔细审查
Djao's beauty, dancing and singing will be scrutinised.
几个小时后就是他的演出了
His big performance is just hours away.
我正在化妆...
因为我想赢得一个姑娘
男人们用彩色粘土
The men decorate themselves
装饰自己
with coloured clays from the desert...
用烧焦的白鹭骨头粉末
..With the crushed, charred bones of egrets
做唇彩涂唇
for their black lipstick,
抹上沙漠植物制作的香水
and with perfumes from desert plants
让他们的魅力更加无法抵挡
to make themselves irresistible.
该迪吉奥上场随乐起舞了
It's time for Djao to face the music.
女人们正在仔细挑选着男人
The men come under close scrutiny from an opinionated crowd.
一行舞者离开后  迪吉奥登场了
As one line of dancers leave, Djao steps into the arena.
他渴望获得三位评委的青睐
He's desperate to be chosen by one of the three girl judges
然后共赴云雨
for a night of desert passion.
女人们逐项审查着
The girls are looking for specific things.
他必须如白鹭般沉稳
He must keep great poise, like an egret.
展示他的牙齿
He must show his teeth,
一展歌喉
flutter his lips and sing from his throat.
还要在有限的时间内翩翩起舞
He must dance in time
并靠肩膀与左右对齐
and use his shoulders to keep his position in the line.
那个男人很帅
迪吉奥有了压力
The pressure's on for Djao.
任何一个小疏忽  都会让他七年的等待付之流水
Any slip now, and he'll lose what he's waited seven years for.
五个小时以后  答案就要揭晓
After five hours, it's the moment of truth.
三位评审选出了她们心目中的冠军
All three judges approach to choose their champions.
第一位评委走到他们面前
The first walks up the line
不经意的一个手势  便选出了心中的白马王子
and, with a subtle gesture, indicates the man of her dreams.
但她没选迪吉奥
But she doesn't choose Djao.
第二位也没选
Neither does the second.
第三位还是没选
Nor the third.
迪吉奥失去了机会
Djao has missed his chance.
他尽了最大的努力却无法赢得一位情人
His best efforts weren't enough to win a lover.
至少得再等上一年
It'll be at least a year
才有机会再次参加比赛了
before he has the opportunity to dance again.
笛贝在找迪吉奥
Tembe is looking for Djao.
许多速配的夫妇开始了约会
Many new couples are hanging out,
但至少迪吉奥和笛贝还拥有彼此
but at least Djao and Tembe still have each other.
你爱我  才会为我编头发
男人女人们都离开了
So the men and women disperse,
有新欢  也有旧爱
some with new lovers, some with old,
每一个人都在返回隔绝的沙漠中前
but all have been touched by the flush of fertility and community
体验到了这场社交盛宴所带来的欢愉
before they return to the isolation of the desert.
沙漠是一幅画风粗犷  朴实无华的画卷
Deserts are landscapes of brutal simplicity.
它们付出甚少  却要求甚多
They provide so little and demand so much.
但只要勇气尚在
But, with courage,
坚韧不拔  才智过人
with endurance and intelligence...
虔诚奉献  匠心独运
..with devotion and ingenuity...
哪怕水资源极度匮乏
..desert people have found ways
沙漠中的人民也能唤起生命的奇迹
to conjure life from so little water.
尽管面对极大的困难  但这里的人们
Against the odds, they have
将对水的渴求  换化为对生的渴望
turned a life of thirst into a thirst for life.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
唯有航拍  才能真正展示图布妇女
The only way to reveal the truly epic nature
横穿撒哈拉沙漠这一史诗般的行为
of the Tubu women's Sahara crossing was to film from the air.
希尼布勒这种小动力热气球
The best tool for this job was a Cinebulle-
即是最佳航拍工具
a hot-air balloon with a small motor.
但热气球不易操纵  驼群喜怒无常
But temperamental technology and cantankerous camels
这使得沙漠拍摄工作难以顺利开展
combined to make this the hardest desert shoot of all.
尼日尔  加索洛勒姆
北纬16°49'07"  东经11°17'00''
历经三天的长途跋涉
It took three days of hard driving
摄影师托比・斯郎和他的团队
before cameraman Toby Strong and
终于追上图布妇女  开始录制工作
the crew could reach the women and start filming.
沙漠中行车  十分困难
Driving in the desert, it's so difficult.
这沙地凹凸不平
You've got all these ridges, troughs.
托比・斯郎
摄影师
大家都这这样下坡的
The guys are going down stuff
车总是陷进沙里
like this and we're getting stuck all the time.
大家寸步难行  只能下车
That means everyone stopping, everyone out.
真挺让人失望的  但这是
It's frustrating, but it's the
自然疯狂的本性  人在沙漠身不由己
nature of the beast. We're here in the desert.
他们终于到达了发射点  开始组装希尼布勒
They reach the launch site and start assembling the Cinebulle.
这是丹尼・克莱耶特・马里奥为摄制组量身打造的
Dany Cleyet-Marrel designed it specifically for filming.
在小引擎的带动下  希尼布勒极适合在
With only small engine, it flies best in the cool morning air
刮着微风的寒冷早晨航行
with no more than a light breeze.
这是我第一次乘坐希尼布勒
This is my first time up in a... in a Cinebulle.
我的两位摄影师朋友会和我一起
I've got two friends, two cameramen, who've been up in this.
据说  第一架希尼布勒撞树失事
The first one, they crashed into a tree,
第二架  引擎起火
and on the second occasion, that caught fire, the actual engine.
我们等下会飞上天空
What I think we're gonna do is go up,
我没跟他们老实交代我的体重
and I might have lied a little bit about how heavy I am,
可能要多带一点燃料
so we might find out that he needs a little more gas.
现在他们正在试飞
Kind of a bit of test flight, like that.
但驼群完全不按套路出牌
But the camels haven't read the schedule
它们四散而去
and they've gone to the four corners.
每晚  牧人都要解开绳索  让驼群自由觅食
Every night, the camels are released to search for food.
清晨  又要颇费周折地将它们聚集起来
So, each morning, it takes time to round them up again.
我们得出发了  不然就太晚了
OK, we have to go, we have to go. It will be too late after.
驼群集中完毕
When the camels are finally ready,
托比和丹尼升入空中  拍摄妇女装货
Toby and Dany set off to film the women loading up.
但拍摄并不顺利
But the shoot doesn't go well.
刚才气球起飞后
What happened was, the balloon took off,
特潘斯・斯通
《人类星球》制片人
经过一夜  丁烷气的温度很低
the butane gas has been cold overnight,
导致引擎熄火
and the burner was cutting out.
他们差点在妇女和驼群上方坠落
They almost came down within the women and the camels.
气球坠落  撞向地面  又再次升起
And then the balloon came down, bounced, took off again,
驼群受惊了
completely freaking out the camels.
出师不利
So not a very good start to the morning.
引擎四次熄火
We lost the burner four times,
气球冲着图布妇女儿童和驼群降下来
plummeted down over the camels, the Tubu women and the kids.
显然把她们吓坏了  其实我也有点害怕
Obviously, freaked them out. Freaked me out a little bit.
首战告败
So that wasn't great on the first flight.
经过几次尝试后  托比终于可以敏锐地捕捉风向
After a few more flights, Toby becomes acutely aware of the wind.
操纵希尼布勒  和开船的原理差不多
Working with Cinebulles is almost exactly like a boat.
你必须顺风行驶
You've got the wind going in that direction
虽然希尼布勒有引擎
and, although the Cinebulle's got a motor,
但也无法逆风而行
you can't really go against the wind.
所以机会只有一次
So you've really only got one pop at each shot.
风向很难掌握
Difficult with the wind.
我们全力对抗大风
We're fighting the wind too much
引擎飞速工作  颤动十分明显
engine's revving and there's vibration and shake.
摇镜拍摄的角度非常小
I've only got a very limited arc to pan around.
所以拍出好画面  很大程度上要仰仗
So there's a huge amount of skill involved from Dany
丹尼和地面上的工作人员
and the guys on the ground
将驼群赶到正确的地方
getting the camels going the right way.
这是一个浩大的工程
So it's a massive logistical operation.
一开始  燃气给我们出难题
In the beginning we had a problem with the gas,
丹尼・克莱耶特・马里奥
希尼布勒操纵员
接着  风向又给我们添麻烦
and after, a problem with the wind.
但明天一定会更好
But tomorrow will be better.
第二天早起飞行  大家又遇到了新麻烦
The next day, after an early flight, they face another problem.
图布妇女不会等待摄制组把希尼布勒装车
The Tubu women don't hang around for the crew
而长时间停留在此处
to pack up the Cinebulle.
她们储备的物资
They only have enough provisions
仅能维持正常穿越沙漠的旅程
for a normal trek across the desert,
所以  摄制组不得不采取"追拍"的策略
so the team has to play catch-up.
我现在真不知道驼群去了哪里
We've no idea where our camels have gone.
她们有25头骆驼
There's 25 camels out there.
你觉得找到它们易如反掌  实则不然
You'd think we'd find them, but it's not...
你四下看看
you know, you look around and
一片荒芜的沙海
it is just like an ocean with a gentle swell.
我们漫无目的  驾车越过一座又一座沙丘
So we're just driving round peak to peak,
希望尽快看见她们
seeing if we can spot them.
好消息是  我们找到了驼队的"丝绸之路"
Good news, we've hit the main caravan route,
有点点像沙漠中的M6公路
which is a bit like... bit like the M6,
更棒的是
and even better news,
有几头骆驼就走在这路上
there's a few groups of camels coming this way.
那些比我眼力好的伙计说
The boys, with better eyes than I,
这就是我们要找的驼队了
say they think that this is some of our group,
这绝对是个好消息
so it's good news.
好的
驼队准备到位
With the camels in place,
托比和丹尼终于等到了
Toby and Dany at last see the
拍摄的绝佳机会
opportunity for getting some really good shots.
-还不错  -很好
- Not so bad. - It's nice.
我们拍的几组镜头还是不错的
I think we've got some nice shots.
最后  我们飞得很高
And then at the end, we went up really high,
整个沙漠尽在眼前  十分壮观
and to see the whole desert opened up was extraordinary.
真是次不错的经历
That was a good flight.
他们取得了一点成就  但前方还有更大的挑战
They've had some success, but the biggest challenge lies ahead
即  拍摄妇女抵达水井的场景
filming the women's arrival at the well.
但在这个沙尘四起的夜里
But on a dusty night,
节目的主角突然人间蒸发
the stars of the show go missing.
我们用探照灯做信号
We've just been using our big spotlight as a beacon,
因为今夜  有三个妇女和六头骆驼
because three of the women and six of the camels
没能赶到营地
couldn't make it into camp tonight
而在沙漠中
and here in the desert,
人员失踪的事时有发生
there's a very good chance of people getting lost.
庆幸的是  办法奏效了
Thankfully, it worked,
大家都安全回到营地过夜
so everyone is safely into camp for the night,
这真是个好消息
which is brilliant news.
只有当太阳落山后
It's only when the sun's gone down
托比才有时间解决个人问题
that Toby has time to deal with a domestic problem.
我们从英国带了30个大箱子来
We brought out 30-odd cases from England.
但其中一个遗失了  里面全是我的衣服
One bag didn't turn up, and that bag was my clothes.
没时间等行李了  要赶紧进沙漠拍摄
So, couldn't wait for it, had to come into the desert,
所以我才老用限量的水
and that is why I'm washing my shirt quite regularly
洗我的衬衣
in, er...my allowance of water.
我当然不会浪费
None of this goes to waste.
明天要用这些水煮茶
This water will be used for... for tea tomorrow.
骗你的啦
No, it won't.
翌日清晨  成败在此一举
The next morning is the most important one.
经过沙漠中的漫长征程
The women are due to arrive at the well
妇女们即将到达水井
after days of navigating across the desert.
托比能否捕捉到这一瞬间  至关重要
It's crucial that Toby gets shots of them arriving,
但和往常一样  拍摄过程困难重重
but, as usual, there are difficulties.
这一拍摄过程包括  发现水井
The logistics involved of finding where the well is
然后飞一大圈
and then driving the whole
以避免拍摄到轮胎的痕迹
way round so as not to get any tyre tracks.
丹尼要摸准风向
Dany having to guess where the wind's coming from.
我们费尽周折辗转到此处
The whole logistical operation
都是为了捕捉这一瞬间
of getting right here, for this point, is enormous
我们一定会成功的
and we've just about managed to get it right.
大家各就各位  一切准备就绪
We're all here, we're ready to go.
风向十分理想  丹尼猜得正好
The wind is perfect. Dany got it spot-on.
45分钟后  驼队就会出现
And the camels are maybe 45 minutes away.
这还挺让人懊恼的
So, it's... it's massively frustrating.
好极了  驼队还没出现
Now it's absolutely perfect. No camels.
和往常一样  骆驼在夜里自由觅食
Yet again, the camels have gone off foraging in the night,
而后随着太阳升起  它们出现在地平线上
then, at last, as the sun rises, they appear over the horizon.
天时地利人和
Everything comes together.
妇女和驼队已经到位  四下无风
The women and the camels are ready, and, with no wind,
托比披着晨曦  绕着驼队飞行
Toby is able to move around them in the early light,
抓拍这一副神奇的画面
capturing a magical scene.
妇女们渐渐接近
As the women close in on the town
旅程的终点  法切镇
of Fachi at the end of the trek,
摄制组终于可以松一口气  将一切问题抛诸脑后
the crew can finally relax, with their problems behind them.
好极了  这次飞行十分精彩
Nice. It was a very, very nice flight.
光线不错  风速也恰到好处
Nice light. Good speed of wind.
我们好像有麻烦了  我以为我们着陆的地点
We've got a problem. I thought we landed far
远离城镇  这样就不会挡别人的路
enough away from town to be out of everyone's way.
但你看地平线那的一群小黑点
But lurking to the horizon and there are hundreds of specks
向这边飞奔而来  我猜他们大概三分钟内
running this way. I reckon we've got three minutes
就会围过来
before we're completely engulfed.
丹尼应该是去迎他们了
I think Dany's off to, er... intercept the hordes.
你好
你给我们带礼物了吗
没有礼物
这些小孩一定兴奋死了
Those kids must be so excited.
看来丹尼得好好"招待"他们一下了
I think Dany's got a bit of a treat for them.
一  二  三...
最令人欣喜的是
To the delight of all,
摄制组不仅排除了艰难万险
the crew have triumphed against the odds...
还搞定了那些执拗的驼群
and the stubborn camels.